If it wasn't apparent before 2026, it
certainly is now. The straight of Hormuz
is one of, if not the most important
maritime choke points in the world. Due
to a freak circumstance in both
geography and geology, roughly half of
all of the world's proven oil reserves
are located around the Persian Gulf west
of the narrow straight of Hormuz. As a
result, because of the combined exports
of countries around the Gulf like Iran,
Iraq, Kuwait, Saudi Arabia, Bahrain,
Qatar, and the UAE, roughly 1ifth of all
the entire world's crude oil and LG
supplies travel through the straight of
Hormuz in a given year, which is the
lifeblood that primarily fuels the
economies of Asia like India, China,
Japan, South Korea, and Southeast Asia.
And on top of all of that oil and gas,
approximately 30% of the world's supply
of fertilizer transits through the
straight as well. While the notoriously
arid Gulf states also import about 85%
of their collective food supply through
the strait as well. The ability for Iran
to enforce a blockade over the straight
and shut all of this trade down was
historically always viewed as being a
theoretical doomsday sort of scenario
that would probably never actually
happen. For decades, expert analysis had
long concluded that the consequences
Iran would suffer by blockading the
strait were going to be too great for
them to ever even try. It was assumed
that Iran would require a massive
military effort to shut down the strait.
It was assumed that Iran would be
reluctant to shut down the strait out of
a fear of invoking a retaliatory
blockade on their own oil exports
through Hormuz that similarly funds a
third of their own government. And it
was assumed that Iran would be fearful
of shutting down the strait because it
would inevitably incur a massive
overwhelming military response from the
United States that would threaten the
survival of the regime itself. But as it
turned out, in the end, all of those
historical expert assumptions held for
decades were proven to be brutally
wrong. After the US and Israel launched
a massive war against Iran with regime
change as the openly stated objective,
the regime felt as if they had nothing
left to lose by shutting down the
straight of Ormos and holding the trade
through it hostage. And they ended up
being able to do it for months with
nothing other than cheap mass-produced
drones, small vessels, and naval mines.
But they were also able to continue
exporting all of their own oil through
the strait until the US Navy eventually
imposed their own blockade on the
straight on Iranian shipping. The entire
might of the US military from all of its
bases in the Middle East and from no
less than three forward deployed
aircraft carrier strike groups proved
incapable of breaking Iran's grip over
the straight. The shutdown of all the
trade through the strait, including the
immediate blocking of 1ifth of the
world's oil and gas supplies, caused
massive global economic damage and
particularly harmed the Gulf States.
While Washington and Thran have
theoretically agreed to negotiate a more
permanent peace deal, the Hormo's genie
also can ever be put back in the bottle
again. Now, Iran's success at shutting
the strait down for so long and forcing
the US and Israel to the negotiating
table in the process has made the
Islamic Republic realize just how much
geographic power and leverage they truly
have. Iran now plainly understands that
it can simply continue to hold Hormuz
and the global economy hostage whenever
it wants something else from the world
again at any point in the future. and
that nobody, not even the mighty US
military, will be capable of actually
stopping them. That lesson that Iran has
learned has also not been lost on the
Gulf States, who themselves now realize
that they need to rapidly diversify
their exports and imports away from
Hormuz or they'll continue facing this
Iranian blackmail repeatedly again in
the future that they won't be able to do
anything to stop. Two of the countries
of the Persian Gulf, Saudi Arabia and
the UAE, had both the geographic
potential and the foresight to have made
contingency plans around Hormuz before
this war. During the 1980s, when Iraq
and Iran were at war with each other and
both of them were busy blasting merchant
shipping across the Persian Gulf, Saudi
Arabia decided that it would be
strategically prudent to build a new
pipeline across their country's
territory from the oil fields in the
Persian Gulf over to their Red Sea
coastline so that they could divert at
least some of their oil exports around
the straight of Hormuz during a time of
crisis. simply called the East West
pipeline. It was constructed precisely
out of the fear that Iran could one day
shut down the straight of Hormuz and to
hedge against it. Then after theory
became reality in early 2026 with Iran
actually shutting the straight down, the
Saudis were able to use the East West
pipeline to divert approximately 7
million barrels of oil per day from the
Persian Gulf to the Red Sea around
Vermuz. an enormous volume that
effectively represented the entirety of
Saudi Arabia's usual export volume. Iran
attempted to target the East West
pipeline with drone and missile attacks
during the war, but it proved to be a
very difficult target to actually hit.
The vast majority of the East West
pipeline is buried several feet
underground, which makes it effectively
invisible to most aerial sensors and
attacks. And then, even if you didn't
know the exact route, hitting the
pipeline beneath the ground requires
incredible accuracy. While explosions
are also mostly absorbed by the ground,
which makes it difficult to damage large
sections of it. Iran targeted some of
the pipelines more vulnerable above
ground pumping stations with missiles
and drones instead. But the Saudis were
always able to quickly repair the
inflicted damage within only a matter of
days. In the end, the East West pipeline
enabled Saudi Arabia to be hardly
affected by Iran's closure of the
Straight of Hormuz at all. In April of
2026, more than a month deep into the
war, the IMF reported that it projected
Saudi Arabia's economy to still grow by
3.1% across the year, down only 1.4
percentage points from its pre-war
projection. Similar to the Saudis, the
UAE also had a pre-existing hedge in
place to get around Iran's closure of
the Straight of Hormuz, too, but it
proved less adequate than the Saudis
workaround did. Dubbed the Hamshan
Fujira oil pipeline or also the Abu
Dhabi crude oil pipeline. The UAE opened
this pipeline in the summer of 2012 for
precisely the same reason that the
Saudis had built their east west
pipeline to reduce their strategic
dependency on sending their oil exports
through the straight of Hormuz. It
enables the UAE to pump oil from the
Persian Gulf to the city of Fujiro which
is safely on the other side of the
straight of Hormuz on the Gulf of Oman.
However, it only enabled the UAE to move
around 1.8 million barrels of oil per
day around the straight of Hormuz during
the war, which was only about half of
their pre-war exports. So, the UAE was
incapable of getting the other half of
their usual exports out of the country
during the war. And this is a
disadvantage that they never intend to
experience again. They are already
fast-tracking the construction of a
brand new twin pipeline to follow along
the route of the existing Abu Dhabi
pipeline, which will effectively double
their export capacity around the
straight of Hormuz and enable them to
continue exporting pretty much all of
their usual oil in the event that the
strait gets shut down again in the
future. This new twin pipeline to Hujyra
is currently expected to be finished and
operational by the end of 2027. And when
it's done, both Saudi Arabia and the UAE
will be able to divert nearly all of
their usual oil exports around the
straight of Hormuz in the event of
another crisis, significantly reducing
Iran's potential leverage over them. The
other countries in the Persian Gulf,
however, by the circumstances of
geography are not as fortunate. Qatar,
Bahrain, Kuwait, and Iraq all possess no
geographic ability to circumvent the
straight of Hormuz across their own
territory. Instead, these countries all
have to rely on the graces of their
neighbors during the Hormuz crisis to
continue their usual exports and
imports, which makes their abilities to
resist Iran's closure of the straight of
Hormuz significantly more challenging.
To illustrate the consequences of this,
consider the divergence and economic
projections right now for 2026 between
Saudi Arabia and Qatar. As I previously
noted, the IMF expects that Saudi
Arabia's economy will grow by 3.1% in
2026, down only 1.4 4 percentage points
from their pre-war forecast. Largely
because Saudi Arabia was still able to
transfer the vast majority of their oil
exports around the closed straight of
Hormuz. Qatar with no such geographic
possibility has a dramatically worse
outcome. Now the IMF currently projects
that cutter's economy will contract by
8.6% this year largely as a result of
the war and the blockage on all of their
LG exports moving through Hormuz for
months. And that's after their economy
grew by 2.8% the year previously in
2025.
Qatar, Bahrain, and Kuwait all currently
have no pipelines that connect anywhere
beyond the Persian Gulf, while Iraq has
very few. Almost all of Iraq's oil
reserves are either concentrated in the
south near the Persian Gulf or in the
mountainous north in the Kurdish
majority areas. As a result, more than
90% of Iraq's oil exports have
historically moved through the Persian
Gulf, which means that after Iran shut
the straight of Hormuz down, Iraq's oil
exports completely collapsed along with
the country's oil production. All four
of these countries had few alternatives
to get around Iran's blockage of the
Straight of Hormuz, and so they were all
forced to largely improvise their
logistics on the spot. Iraq came up with
a route they called the pipeline on
wheels. A trucking route from the oil
fields in Iraqi Kurdistan that
transported oil and trucks across Syria
toward the Bayas refinery and export
facilities on the Syrian Mediterranean
coast, which was able to safely
transport around 200,000 barrels of oil
per day around the Straight of Hormuz
closure. While impressive, that still
only represented about 6% of Iraq's
pre-war oil exports. The only other
route that Iraq had around the straight
of Hormuz was its Kirkook Seahan oil
pipeline extending from the oil fields
in Iraqi Kurdistan through Turkey to the
Turkish port of Seahan on the
Mediterranean. However, it too only has
a maximum capacity of around 200,000
barrels per day, a fraction of Iraq's
usual production capacity. In the
aftermath of the war, Iraq is now
seeking to nearly quadruple the Kirkooky
oil pipelines capacity to 770,000
barrels per day instead. And they plan
to accomplish it within only a few
months time. Before the war, the port of
Cororakan on the UAE's Gulf of Oman
coast primarily served as a trans
shshipment port. Containers arrived by
ship and were transferred directly onto
another ship, and very few containers
actually left the port by road. Only
around a 100 trucks a day usually even
did so. But after the straight of Hormuz
shut down, all of that changed
dramatically. Horakan suddenly became
the UAE's primary gateway port outside
of Hormuz, enabling ships arriving from
Europe, Asia, and Africa to unload
without having to cross through Hormuz
into the Persian Gulf. Containers could
be unloaded at Cororicon and then driven
on highways inland which proved to be a
godsend for maintaining the imports of
food and other goods for the UAE, Saudi
Arabia, Qatar, Bahrain, Kuwait, and Iraq
during the war. In a flash, the number
of trucks arriving at Coricon exploded
from only around a hundred a day to more
than 7,000 a day, while the numbers of
weekly container movements through the
port exploded from about 2,000 to 50,000
as well. Almost overnight, the Arab
states around the Persian Gulf
essentially recreated the historical
overland caravan routes across the
deserts that they had used to rely upon
before the advent of large-scale
maritime trade through the Gulf. But
while trucking around the straight of
Hormos proved sufficient enough for
imports of food and other consumer
goods, it was never going to be
sufficient enough to replace oil
exports. A popular meme that surfaced on
the internet during the war was this
idea posted to X by a man named Harsh
Gena, an Indian billionaire
industrialist who proposed trucking oil
through the deserts of Arabia round the
straight of Hormuz. It was accompanied
by scathing commentary like, "Bro thinks
they can just mad max a couple million
barrels of crude through the deserts of
Oman every day." In reality, replacing
all of the lost oil exports through the
straight of Hormuz trucking was never
going to be feasible. The area of the
Arabian Peninsula between the Persian
Gulf and the Arabian Sea is known as the
Raal Khali or the empty quarter. A vast,
inhospitable, and almost completely
empty desert with very few roads and
other infrastructure traversing anywhere
across it. As a result, somebody on a
Reddit thread about this meme calculated
that it would take a minimum of 55,000
tanker trucks just to match the capacity
that usually flows through the straight
of muzz. It would mean filling up and
sending off a truck every 0.8 seconds,
24 hours a day. And if you placed all of
these trucks end to end, they'd be twice
as long as the entire current route
through the desert and back. Which means
that the Saudis and Omanis would have to
construct dramatically more road
infrastructure through one of the most
inhospitable environments on Earth to
meet the demand. That's not something
that can be accomplished on such short
notice, obviously, which means that
trucking all of the lost oil around the
straight of Armos was never going to be
a feasible option during wartime. Now,
in the aftermath of the war, there were
multiple logistical strategies floating
around in the Persian Gulf to eliminate
everybody's remaining overdependency on
the straight of Formos going forward.
Cutter is usually the world's leading
exporter of liqufied natural gas or LNG.
But as is obvious, all of Qatar's LG
exports have no choice but to travel
through the straight of Orbuz. And when
it's blocked, they currently have no
alternative. To resolve this, Cutter
would need to either construct a gas
pipeline through the UAE's territory to
either Fujira or Oman, or they would
need to construct a much longer gas
pipeline through the territory of Saudi
Arabia to the Red Sea, or even further
across Saudi territory in the countries
of the Levant towards the Mediterranean
coast. And none of these options are
particularly palatable for them.
Wherever the pipelines end up at, Cutter
would need to construct brand new ultra
expensive liquefaction facilities
outside of the Gulf in order to turn the
gas into liquid for export on board the
tanker ships, which will increase the
cost required for them substantially. At
the same time, cutter would be
effectively exchanging their dependence
on Iran for exports through the straight
of muzz towards a dependence on the UAE
or Saudi Arabia for pipeline exports
instead. two countries whom cutters had
highly strained relations with in the
recent past. It wasn't that long ago,
just between 2017 and 2021, when both
Saudi Arabia and the UAE severed their
relations with Qatar and enforced a
complete land, sea, and air blockade
over the country. So, Qatar would be
reluctant to put their critical
alternative gas export routes through
either of these countries, but they also
don't really have any other option. One
of the biggest obstacles standing in the
way of the Gulf States from diversifying
their logistics around the straight of
Hormuz historically was the inconvenient
space on the board that was occupied by
the Assad regime in Syria. For more than
half a century, while the Assad family
dominated Syria, Syria's foreign policy
was kept in close alignment with the
Iranians and the Russians and in fierce
opposition to the Western world. That
along with the devastating civil war
that wrecked Syrian society for more
than 13 years between 2011 and 2024
meant that the geographic space occupied
by Syria was long off limits to
pipelines and trucking routes for the
Gulf States who were attempting to build
alternative infrastructure paths around
the straight of muzz. This elimination
of Syria's geography from consideration
in addition to the elimination of
Israel's geography because of the Arab
state's opposition to Israel meant that
in recent history the only possible path
for pipelines and trucks to take away
from the Persian Gulf towards the
Mediterranean had to take the long route
through Iraq through the Zagros
mountains in northern Iraq and then
across Turkeykey's Anatolian Peninsula
towards the Turkish Mediterranean coast
instead. In 2024, before the Assad
regime unexpectedly collapsed, the Iraqi
government approved of a new crude oil
pipeline project from their southern oil
fields to the Jordanian port of Akaba,
the Red Sea, through only Iraqi and
Jordanian territory, avoiding both Syria
and Israel. Two years later, in May of
2026, more than a month deep into the
Iran war and the closure of the straight
of Hormuz, Iraq announced that
construction on this Bazra Akaba
pipeline had finally been fast-tracked
and begun. And that once it was
finished, it would enable the Iraqis to
transfer roughly 2.5 million barrels of
oil per day around the straight of
Hormuz to the Red Sea, or about 70% of
their usual total oil exports. $1.5
billion for the project has already been
committed. Although no completion date
has yet been officially announced.
Whenever it is finished, however, in
combination with the pipeline on wheels
and the projected expansion of the
Kirkook Seahan crude oil pipeline, Iraq
will be able to join both Saudi Arabia
and the UAE and being able to divert
nearly all of their oil exports around
the straight of Hormuz during another
crisis in the future. The geographic
advantage of being able to run pipelines
through serious territory towards the
Mediterranean coastline was always
widely recognized by everyone from very
early on, of course, but history and
geopolitics just frequently interveneed
to make any pipelines across Syrian
territory effectively impossible. After
Syria first gained their independence
from France in 1946, the US heavily
backed the construction of the
Transarabian Pipeline or TAP line from
the giant oil fields of Saudi Arabia on
the Persian Gulf through Jordanian and
Syrian territory onwards to Lebanon's
Mediterranean coast. However, in order
to take the shortest possible path to
the Mediterranean while avoiding Israel,
the route of Tapline ran through the
Golan Heights region of far southwestern
Syria, which of course was later taken
over by the Israelis during the 6-day
war of 1967. The Israelis then came to
control this section of the Tapline. And
while they continued to allow Saudi oil
to flow through it, the pipeline became
a frequent target of sabotage by
Palestinian militant groups that
degraded its capacity. After years of
nearly constant bickering between the
Saudis and Syria and Lebanon over
transit fees, the emergence of super
tankers moving through the straight of
Wormuz and frequent pipeline breakdowns
due to all of the sabotage attempts, the
section of the pipeline beyond Jordan
extending through the Golan Heights and
Lebanon was permanently shut down in
1976,
eliminating Tapline's direct access to
the Mediterranean. And then the rest of
the pipeline through Jordan was also
shut down by the Saudis in 1990 in
retaliation for Jordan's support of
Saddam Hussein's invasion in conquest of
Kuwait. And it's remained completely
inoperable ever since then. Another
crude oil pipeline across Syria was
constructed in the 1950s between the
Iraqi city of Kirkook and Syria's
Mediterranean port of Badas. But Israeli
forces bombed the pipeline during the
1956 Suez crisis. While later in 1982,
the Assad regime shut the pipeline down
completely after they allied with the
Iranians against Saddam during the Iran
Iraq war. Whatever was left of the
pipeline was then bombed again by the
Americans during the 2003 invasion of
Iraq and has been permanently inoperable
ever since then. The idea of building a
natural gas pipeline from Qatar directly
to Europe via Turkey is another grand
project that's been discussed for
decades now.Qatar Qatar possesses the
third largest proven reserves of natural
gas in the world. But as a tiny
peninsula that's hemmed in by Saudi
Arabia, it has always relied on
exporting its gas in liquid form aboard
tanker ships to markets through the
straight of Hormuz instead of through
pipelines. Constructing a gas pipeline
fromQatar to Europe would benefit Qatar
by providing them with a major bypass
around the straight of Hormuz. While it
would also benefit Europe by providing
them with more direct access to piped
gas fromQatar, reducing the reliance on
piped gas from Russia. The shortest and
most geographically easy route for this
proposed gas pipeline to take has always
been across Saudi Arabia and then
through Jordan and Syria into Turkey and
onwards to Europe. But because of how
the pipeline would inherently reduce
Europe's reliance on Russian gas, the
Russians pressured their allies and the
Assad regime to suddenly abandon all of
their plans for the pipeline completely.
in 2011 and shortly after that the civil
war erupted in Syria that destroyed most
of the pipeline infrastructure in the
country that still remained and which
also kept Syria's territory completely
off limits to any further consideration
for more than a decade. Roughly 6,300 km
worth of oil and gas pipelines still
existed in Syria immediately before the
civil war while the country was also
domestically producing around 380,000
barrels of oil per day. But across the
civil war, the pipelines, pumping
stations, and export facilities in Syria
grew to become symbols of the Assad
regime's authority. In addition to
military objectives and major sources of
revenue, by the time the Assad regime
finally collapsed near the end of 2024,
swaths of Syria's energy transportation
network had been heavily damaged or
looted or otherwise made dysfunctional.
The country's domestic oil production
plummeted from 380,000 barrels per day
pre-war to only 110,000 barrels per day
postwar. While the nation's rail
infrastructure was similarly devastated
as well. Out of the roughly 1,500 miles
worth of railways that existed in Syria
before the war, more than 60% of them
were either damaged or knocked out of
service throughout the course of the
war, leaving only about 600 miles left
that are still operational today that
are usually under very heavy
constraints. Thus, Syria has a long
history going back decades now of having
pipelines running across its territory
getting targeted and destroyed during
conflicts. [music] And so the newly
stabilized government that's taken over
the country since 2024 certainly has
their work cut out to show that that
history won't also be its future. Still,
now that the long civil war in Syria is
generally seen as being over and with
the anti-western Assad regime out of the
picture, there might finally be an
opportunity to take advantage of Syria's
geography as a natural energy corridor
between the Persian Gulf and Europe.
Akban al-Shara, Syria's new president,
has recently proposed reviving the old
but still never realized four seas
project, which envisions transforming
Syria into a central logistics node for
pipelines, railways, and highways,
linking the Mediterranean, the Persian
Gulf, the Caspian, and Black Seas all
together, and turning Syria into an
alternative overland logistics corridor
around both the straight of Hormuz and
the Suez Canal, which have been
frequently menaced by Iran and the
Houthis in Yemen. And in many ways, this
vision is already starting to take a
little bit of hold. The pipeline on
wheels, the oil trucking route between
northern Iraq and the Syrian coast that
was improvised while Iran was shutting
down the straight of Hormos during the
war is still operational. The old Arab
gas pipeline is once again operational
and carrying Egyptian gas into southern
Syria. While the recently constructed
Kilis Aleppo pipeline is also
operational and carrying Azerbaijani gas
through Turkeykey's pipeline network
into northern Syria. For the Persian
Gulf states, additional major
interlocking infrastructure corridors
across Syria are also currently being
considered as a part of this four seas
initiative. The first between the
Persian Gulf and Syria's Mediterranean
coast consists of two possible projects.
the long discussed natural gas pipeline
from Qatar to Syria that will enable
Qatar to diversify their gas exports
around the straight of Hormuz in
addition to another proposal to revive
the longdefunct tapline corridor between
the oil fields of Saudi Arabia and the
Syrian Mediterranean coast as well
giving the Saudis the ability to
diversify their oil exports around both
the straight of Hormuz and the Suez
Canal. Another corridor between Iraq and
Syria proposes restoring and expanding
the longdefuncted Kirkook Bonnas oil
pipeline as well, giving Iraq another
option to get their own oil exports
around the straight of Hormuz too. To
help facilitate all of these plans, the
Trump administration in the United
States has substantially lifted
sanctions on Syria, including restoring
Syria's access to the Swift global
payments network. Both Chevron and Kako
Phillips have already signed preliminary
agreements with Syria, including the
country's first ever offshore oil and
gas development project, while Qatari US
Turkish consortium have already signed a
multi-billion dollar energy deal with
Syria as well. And in addition to these
pipeline corridors across Syria, new
railways are being planned as well.
Turkey, Jordan, and Syria's new
government have already signed a
trilateral memorandum of understanding
to resurrect the longdefunct Hijazz
Railway, a rail project originally
constructed all the way back during the
Ottoman period that connected Saudi
cities like Medina to Damascus and the
Mediterranean coast. Large sections of
the Hijaz Railway were destroyed by the
Arab revolt during the First World War,
however, and over the decades that
followed, the rest was split apart by
new borders, dismantled for scrap, or
simply abandoned. It has been
dysfunctional for virtually all of
living memory. But reviving it today
could open up a new critical import
route for food for Saudi Arabia and the
Gulf States that currently
overwhelmingly rely on the straight of
Hormuz for 85% of their food imports.
The Saudis have even suggested
developing parts or even all of the
railway as a high-speed train network
with speeds of 125 mph, which would
become the second high-speed railway to
ever open in the Middle East after Saudi
Arabia's own herain high-speed railway
between Mecca, Jedha, and Medina.
Building out all of this infrastructure
across Syria could serve multiple
geopolitical lanes. It can enable the
Persian Gulf states to diversify their
exports and imports away from the
straight of Hormuz and undermine Iran's
capability to hold the global economy
hostage again. It can help Europe
diversify their own energy import
destinations and further reduce their
reliance on Russian energy, while it can
also help underwrite Syria's economic
reconstruction and recovery in the wake
of their civil war through lucrative
transit fees and through kickstarting
their own oil production back up again
as well. Nonetheless, there are still a
lot of headwinds going against the Syria
plan. In 2021, the World Bank estimated
that the cost of fully rebuilding Syria
back to its pre-war level of development
was a staggering $400 billion, which has
no doubt grown over the years of further
war and deterioration since then.
Rebuilding Syria's railway network alone
might cost as much as $5 billion. And
that doesn't even include any of the
plans for restoring the Hijazz Railway
or building out a new high-speed railway
line that didn't even exist pre-war.
Rebuilding Syria's wrecked
infrastructure will be expensive enough,
let alone building out any brand new
infrastructure. While the historical
risks associated with Syria's
instability probably won't just go away
either. Both the proposed cutter gas
pipeline and the restored Kirkook banas
oil pipeline would travel through vast
expanses of sparsely populated desert
where remnants of ISIS and Iranianbacked
Shiite militias continue to remain
active. Meaning that securing the safety
of all of these pipeline routes across
Syria is far from a certainty. While
possibly even more problematically, the
largest and fastest growing energy
market for the Gulf producers isn't even
in Europe at all. It's in the other
direction in Asia. The overwhelming
majority of the Persian Gulf's energy
resources flow to the east, and that
share is continuing to grow with every
passing year as Europe continues to
decarbonize and increases its LG imports
from the United States. Building
massively time-conuming, expensive, and
geopolitically risky infrastructure
across Syria to the Mediterranean works
to get around the straight of Hormuz.
But it's also in the opposite direction
where most of the Persian Gulf's exports
are actually heading towards, which
reduces a lot of the project's potential
usefulness. Nonetheless, the
geopolitical benefits of undermining
what is currently Iran's greatest
geographic advantage, its ability to
threaten and close the straight of
Hormuz might alone outweigh all of the
various possible drawbacks. Iran may
have been able to use this leverage over
Hormuzz to come out ahead during this
most recent war. But if the Gulf States,
America, and Europe can claw that
leverage away from Iran by diversifying
their pipeline and railway routes around
the Straight of Hormuz, Iran might very
well end up losing the peace in the long
term by losing its ability to credibly
do the same thing again in the future.
And in that future, during another
potential conflict with Iran, the
Iranians will be the ones who will be in
the much, much worse position to
negotiate from. Now, if you're anything
like me, your email inbox is probably a
complete disaster. Every website you've
ever made an account on seems determined
to email you forever. Advertisers
somehow always know exactly what you've
been looking at online, and it can be a
little unsettling just how much of your
digital life ends up tied to just a
single email account. The reality is
that email has become the front door to
almost everything we do online, which is
why it's worth using one that's actually
built around privacy instead of
advertising. And that's why this video
is sponsored by Proton Mail. Proton was
created by a group of scientists who met
at CERN that wanted to build an email
service where your data actually belong
to you instead of a big tech company.
Because Proton is based in Switzerland,
it's protected by some of the strongest
privacy laws in the world. And thanks to
their use of end-to-end zero access
encryption, not even Proton itself can
read the contents of your emails. Your
data is truly safely your own. Only if
you've been using Gmail for years,
switching over also isn't nearly as
painful as you might think. Proton's
easy switch feature lets you import all
of your emails and contacts in just a
few clicks. And you can even connect to
your existing Gmail account so you can
send and receive emails from both
inboxes in one place while you
transition at your own pace. And best of
all, you can get started right now
completely for free. Just head to my
link at proton.me/realife
to sign up and start securing your data
today. Using my link will also help
support my channel tremendously at the
same time. And as always, thank you so
much for watching.